<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks | THIYANGA TALAGALA</title>
    <link>/talk/</link>
      <atom:link href="/talk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks</title>
      <link>/talk/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>RMarkdown: Create insightful reports in R</title>
      <link>/talk/nigeria/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/nigeria/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/nigeria/abuja.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why R? 2021: Keynote</title>
      <link>/talk/whyr-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/whyr-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Why R? Foundation held its &lt;a href=&#34;https://2021.whyr.pl/&#34;&gt;Why R? 2021 Conference - the fifth meeting of Central-Eastern-European&lt;/a&gt; in December 2021. I was honored to be asked by this esteemed group to provide a keynote address on Feature-based Time Series Forecasting and join with forecasting and prediction panel discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/whyr/panel.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many applications require a large number of time series to be forecast. Providing better forecasts for these time series is important in decision and policy making. However, large scale time series data present numerous challenges in modelling and implementation due to the high dimensionality. It is unlikely that a single method will consistently provide better forecasts across all time series. On the other hand, selecting individual forecast models when the number of series is very large can be extremely challenging. In this talk, I will present a general framework for forecast model selection using meta-learning. We call this framework FFORMS (Feature-based FORecast Model Selection). The underlying approach involves computing a vector of features from the time series which are then used to select the forecasting model. The model selection process is carried out using a classification algorithm – we use the time series features as inputs, and the best forecasting algorithm as the output. Furthermore, we explore what is happening under the hood of the FFORMS framework and thereby gain an understanding of what features lead to the different choices of forecast models and how different features influence the predicted outcome. The proposed algorithm is implemented in the R package seer, which is available on CRAN at &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=seer&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=seer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seer package: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/thiyangt/seer&#34;&gt;https://github.com/thiyangt/seer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forecasting Model Territories</title>
      <link>/talk/isf21-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/isf21-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The field of time series forecasting has  been evolving rapidly with advances in techniques for modelling and forecasting. However, choosing the right technique for a given series is at the heart of forecasting research. This process is challenging because certain forecasting techniques will perform best on some series while different alternative will perform best on other series. Certainly, each forecasting technique has its own territory and dominance. Discovering the conditions under which a forecasting technique will function well and under which not is useful in identifying model territory and dominance. The forecast submissions of the top 25 participants of the M4-competition are used for the analysis. Evaluating forecasting submission only using global measures such as forecasting error measure collapse all local information and does not allow to identify local differences of those methodologies. We explore the relationships between features of the methodologies used to generate forecasts, features of the resulting forecasts and features of the time series to identify model territories and their characteristics. Taking these local information into account can have benefit in developing new methods and shed some light for further development in the field of forecasting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large-Scale Time Series Forecasting</title>
      <link>/talk/norway21-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/norway21-talk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Tool to Detect Potential Data Leaks in Forecasting Competitions</title>
      <link>/talk/isf20-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/isf20-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-tool-to-detect-potential-data-leaks-in-forecasting-competitions&#34;&gt;A Tool to Detect Potential Data Leaks in Forecasting Competitions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forecasting competitions are of increasing importance as a mean to learn best practices and gain knowledge. Data leakage is one of the most common issues that can often be found in competitions. Data leaks can happen when the training data contains information about the test data. There are a variety of different ways that data leaks can occur with time series data. For example: i) randomly chosen blocks of time series are concatenated to form a new time series, ii) scale-shifts, iii) repeating patterns in time series,  iv) white noise is added in the original time series to form a new time series, etc.  This work introduces a novel tool to detect these data leaks. The tsdataleaks package provides simple and computationally efficient algorithm to exploit data leaks in time series data. I will demonstrate the package design and its power to detect data leakages using recent forecasting competitions data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key words:&lt;/strong&gt; Time series, R software, Tools, Visualization&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feature-based Time Series Forecasting</title>
      <link>/talk/user19-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/user19-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work presents two feature-based forecasting algorithms for large-scale time series forecasting. The
algorithms involve computing a range of features of the time series which are then used to select the forecasting model. The forecasting model selection process is carried out using a pre-trained classifier. In our first algorithm we use a random forest algorithm to train the classifier. We call this framework FFORMS (Feature-based FORecast Model Selection). The second algorithm use efficient Bayesian multivariate surface regression approach to estimate forecast error for each method, and then using the minimum predicted error to select a forecasting model. Both algorithms have been evaluated using time series from the M4 competition, and is shown to yield accurate forecasts comparable to several benchmarks and other commonly used automated approaches in the time series forecasting literature. The methods are made available in the seer and fformpp packages in R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;keywords: Meta-learning, classification, surface regression&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peeking inside FFORMS: Feature-based FORecast Model Selection</title>
      <link>/talk/isf19-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/isf19-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;peeking-inside-fforms-feature-based-forecast-model-selection&#34;&gt;Peeking inside FFORMS: Feature-based FORecast Model Selection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thiyanga S. Talagala$^1$, Rob J. Hyndman$^1$, George Athanasopoulos$^1$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$^1$Department of Econometrics and Business Statistics, Monash University, Australia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Features of time series are useful in identifying suitable forecast models. Talagala, Hyndman &amp;amp; Athanasopoulos (2018) proposed a classification framework, called FFORMS (Feature-based FORecast Model Selection), which selects forecast models based on features calculated from the time series. The FFORMS framework builds a mapping that relates the features of a time series to the “best” forecast model using the random forest algorithm. In this paper we explore what is happening under the hood of the FFORMS framework and thereby gain an understanding of what features lead to the different choices of forecast models and how different features influence the predicted outcome. This is accomplished using model-agnostic machine learning interpretability approaches. Partial-dependency plots are used to visualize both main and interaction effects of features. The results of this study provide a valuable insight into how different features and their interactions affect the choice of forecast model selection. This gives a more refined picture of the relationship between features and the choice of forecast model which is particularly valuable for ongoing research in the field of feature-based time series analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Keywords:&lt;/em&gt;
forecasting, time series, machine learning interpretability, black-box models, LIME&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talagala, TS, RJ Hyndman &amp;amp; G Athanasopoulos (2018). Meta-learning how to forecast time series. Working paper 6/18. Monash University, Department of Econometrics and Business Statistics&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feature-based time series forecasting</title>
      <link>/talk/beijingtalk19-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/beijingtalk19-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work presents three feature-based algorithms for large-scale time series forecasting.  The algorithms are developed based on meta-learning approach. In our first algorithm we use a random forest algorithm to identify the best forecasting model. We call this framework FFORMS (Feature-based FORecast Model Selection).  In the second algorithm, FFORMA (Feature-based FORecast Model Averaging), we use gradient boosting to obtain the weights for forecast combinations. The third algorithm use efficient Bayesian multivariate surface regression approach to estimate forecast error for each method, and then using the minimum predicted error to select a forecasting model or to choose individual models for forecast combinations. The proposed algorithms perform well compared to several benchmarks and other commonly used approaches in large-scale forecasting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A classification framework for forecast-model selection</title>
      <link>/talk/jsm18-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/jsm18-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The background pictures are of free copyright from &lt;a href=&#34;https://pixabay.com/en/photos/presentation/&#34;&gt;https://pixabay.com/en/photos/presentation/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Associated R package: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/thiyangt/seer&#34;&gt;seer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>seer: R package for feature-based forecast model selection</title>
      <link>/talk/user18-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/user18-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seer package provides a novel framework for forecast model selection using time series features. We call this framework FFORMS (Feature-based FORecast Model Selection). The underlying approach involves computing a vector of features from the time series which are then used to select the forecasting model. The model selection process is carried out using a classification algorithm &amp;ndash; we use the time series features as inputs, and the best forecasting algorithm as the output. The classification algorithm can be built in advance of the forecasting exercise (so it is an “offline” procedure). Then, when we have a new time series to forecast, we can quickly compute its features, use the pre-trained classification algorithm to identify the best forecasting model, and produce the required forecasts. Thus, the “online” part of our algorithm requires only feature computation, and the application of a single forecasting model, with no need to estimate large numbers of models within a class, or to carry out a computationally-intensive cross-validation procedure. This framework is compared against several benchmarks and other commonly used forecasting methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link to git repository: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/thiyangt/seer&#34;&gt;seer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meta-learning how to forecast time series</title>
      <link>/talk/isf18-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/isf18-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A crucial task in time series forecasting is the identification of the most suitable forecasting method. We present a general framework for forecast model selection using meta-learning. A Random Forest is used to predict the best forecasting method using only time series features. The proposed framework has been evaluated using time series from the M1 and M3 competitions, and is shown to yield accurate forecasts comparable to several benchmarks and other commonly used automated approaches of time series forecasting. A key advantage of our algorithm is that the time-consuming part of building the random forest can be handled in advance of the forecasting task.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysing large collections of time series</title>
      <link>/talk/japan18-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/japan18-talk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feature-based model selection for time series forecasting</title>
      <link>/talk/isf17-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/isf17-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many applications require a large number of time series to be forecast. Providing better forecasts for these time series is important in decision and policy making. However, large scale time series data present numerous challenges in modelling and implementation due to
the high dimensionality. It is unlikely that a single method will consistently provides better forecasts across all time series. On the other hand, selecting individual forecast models when the number of series is very large can be extremely challenging. In this paper we propose a classification framework which selects forecast models based on features calculated from the time series. A Random Forest approach is used to develop the classifier. The proposed framework is tested using the M3 data and is compared against several benchmarks and other commonly used approaches of forecasting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feature-based model selection for time series forecasting</title>
      <link>/talk/ssa17-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/ssa17-talk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feature-based model selection for time series forecasting</title>
      <link>/talk/ysc17-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/ysc17-talk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
